As a manager, I could get rid of any one
employee I wanted. This was the most
brutally honest interview I've done so
far. I think most pips are a combination
of dishonest and or psychologically
unrealistic.
>> This is Ethan Evans. He went from being
fired twice to being promoted to a VP at
Amazon with a team of over 800
engineers.
>> After it happened twice, I damn sure
looked at like, who's the common element
in this? It's me. I asked him about his
experience working with famous Amazon
executives like Jeff Bezos and Andrew
Jasse.
>> I've probably had about 50 meetings with
him and about 50 with Andy. The biggest
difference is Jeff's
>> I also asked them about the behind the
scenes of performance management at
Amazon. What is stopping a manager from
painting their report in an unfair
light? People won't like to hear this.
I'm actually willing to tell you the
truth and tell you that almost
everyone's doing what I'm doing. They're
just not telling you. Before
we get into, you know, the juicy parts
of you kind of growing to a VP at
Amazon, I think that's a level that a
lot of people can only, you know, dream
of or imagine of. Really curious to dig
into what is even happening at those
levels. I'm curious to kind of lay out
your full career story. I know there's
some interesting stories about you being
uh fired in the com boom prior to
joining Amazon, and I imagine there's a
lot of interesting learnings there. So
let's get into the beginning of your
story which is your experience before
Amazon.
>> Yeah, absolutely. So just to your
original point, I never expected to be a
VP at Amazon. That just kind of evolved
like many careers do. I started working
and that's where I ended up and I'm very
happy with it. I wanted to be an
engineer and I grew up right when home
computers were beginning and so I
actually wrote Apple a letter, a
physical letter pre- email and said,
"Hey, I want to come work at your
company. how do I do that? And they
explained to me that at that time they
only hired engineers from five
universities. Uh Stanford, Caltech,
Berkeley, all in California. I was in
Ohio, so that seemed far. Uh Carnegie
Melon and MIT. I didn't get admitted to
MIT. I did go to Carnegie Melon. And so
I was like on this plan of I will go
work at Apple. What actually happened is
uh I did a master's degree at Purdue and
then I started going through startups
basically all with a thread of
high-speed networking. So the first
company was a physical layer networking.
Had an incredible run there. Got
promoted a couple times, not unlike your
early story. Then I joined an internet
search firm that was acquired by LIOS,
one of the original search engines. From
there I went to a network management
company that worked at the management
layer of large networks for Telos. From
there I went to internet advertising and
audio streaming. The internet couldn't
handle video at that point. I had a
short detour at a company that made
lighting, entertainment lighting, like
dance club stuff. Uh, which an
interesting detour. And then Amazon
hired me and asked me to build Prime
Video based on the the work I had done
streaming uh music. And so there is a a
chain of one after the other, but the
startups were all very different, you
know, very small, very high growth. And
candidly, most of them other than the
first one flamed out right before the
dot. And that's also where I managed to
get myself made redundant twice. So it
wasn't just once, it was really twice.
Both times helped along by the fact that
I was abrasive.
>> I'm kind of curious cuz a lot of people
early in career, there's the decision
between going to smaller companies
versus more established ones. What was
your thinking behind working at
startups? Well, like a lot of people, I
guess my original thinking was driven by
my friends. I had friends who had joined
this startup that was local to Carnegie
Melon in Pittsburgh. It was founded by
some professors who'd left. Uh they were
talking about how cool it was and they
were getting me things called stock
options, which at that time, because I'm
older, no one I'd never heard of and
they were explaining it. I'm like, "Wow,
that seems amazing." And so, it wasn't
really a conscious choice of small or
big. It was this apparent gold mine and
my roommate who had joined a little
earlier. So my college roommate who then
was my roommate when I started in in his
company also he joined a little earlier
than I did. He joined before that
company IPOed and he made his first
million dollars by the time he was 25 or
26 with inflation. Now that would be
like two or three million. You know it
worked incredibly well. It was the
startup dream. I joined a little later.
I only made enough money to put a down
payment on a house. But still, I think
the real estate agent was pretty
surprised when I was probably 25 and,
you know, putting cash down on a house.
I went that way because that's where my
friends went. It wasn't until later that
I really started understanding what does
a career look like and making
intentional choices.
>> You mentioned being made redundant twice
or I assume that means exiting the
company,
>> let go, laid off. Yeah. You mentioned it
was because you were abrasive. Did you
see it coming? And what's the story
behind uh those layoffs?
>> Oh, I'd love to tell you I saw it
coming. It's not that people didn't try
and warn me. My very first performance
review I ever got, my manager said, I
think sometimes Ethan's solution to
problems would be, "Let's knock their
heads together." You know, so I was I
was pretty combative. He saw it. I
didn't get let go at that company, but
you know, this was a consistent theme. I
used to say uh you probably know the the
phrase, "Oh, that person's a loose
cannon." Well, I modified it as, "Oh,
yeah, people say I'm a loose cannon, but
that's only because I'm pointed at them,
right? I'm I'm busy telling them how
wrong they are." Uh, so obviously that
whole statement, I'm busy telling them
how wrong they are, is very arrogant.
That was me. So, as I went up in
leadership levels, I rose based on
ability and and jumping into projects. I
rose to a vice president in startup
level. But then I had conflict with my
peers. The first peer was a product guy.
He was basically saying, "We are
dreaming that we're going to build all
the things we're going to build in the
time we're going to build them." He was
predicting that our product was
impossible to put together with the time
and resources we had. He was actually
right. I was fantasizing. I I was mad
that he wasn't committed to the mission.
So, I ended up fighting with him because
he was saying something that was true,
but it wasn't lined up with my religion,
which is, "But we're a startup team
together. We're gonna do it." And he was
pushing back on that enthusiasm. So, we
argued that company hit hard times. I
wasn't let go only because of that, but
we were downsizing and I had an
opportunity at another startup. And so
part of what I did is I talked to the
CEO and I said, 'Look, I have the chance
to just bounce to this other startup and
you can save someone else. And he's
like, "That sounds great." Well, in
hindsight, of course, he was probably
also pretty glad to get rid of the
contention in his team. Fast forward to
the next startup, classic situation. I
was leading engineering and the sales
VP, we were short on money because it
was the.com bus. The sales VP was lying
about what the product would do. He was
talking it up and making a sale based on
stuff we hadn't built. And of course, as
the head of engineering, I'm like, we
don't we can't, you know, I was arguing
with him about we can't do that. The
thing I didn't realize was it was either
sign that contract or go out of
business. And so, you know, the the fact
is the truthfulness there matters, but
he needed to promise the sun, the moon,
and the stars, and then we would have to
do our best to deliver it or go under.
Well, again, in that case, I really was
um let go and it was technically a
layoff, but I was the only person laid
off in the layoff. So, they called it a
layoff. They presented it to me as a
layoff, but you know, you're the only
one in the room being laid off. I'd call
that being fired. That was 100% about
removing conflict. So, you asked, did I
see it coming? The important thing I
would say is no, but after it happened
twice, I damn sure looked at like, who's
the common element in this? it's me and
why why is that? And while I was sitting
around in a in a bad period of the
economy trying to find a new job and
struggling to do so, I absolutely asked
what do I need to change? What do I need
to be do differently? And so it was
after that I completely yeah completely
I very significantly changed my
personality. I changed how I interacted
at work to not get into you know
arguments and shouting matches with
people. Now I just handle those very
differently. I ask questions. I listen.
People don't steamroll me, but I don't
escalate confrontation.
>> You mentioned that, you know, soft
skills obviously became an important
part of you being a leader, but when you
were earlier in your career, you were a
little bit more abrasive. You kind of
went in the direction that you thought
was right. No one would doubt that soft
skills are important, but I'm kind of
curious like early career. Do you think
being abrasive and super aggressive on
your direction was actually better or do
you think it would have been even better
if you had soft skills? I mean, I think
if I had had soft skills with that
energy, it would have been the best. But
even today, I tell people, look, you
have to be somewhat pushy. The best
phrase someone recently taught me or
used, they called it being strategically
annoying. And I like that because
annoying isn't as bad as abrasive or
confrontational, but it gets at that you
can't just be compliant or helpful.
You've got to have an opinion and be
willing to fight for it. It's really a
question of how do you fight? I was
fighting more in the classic way of
getting red in the face or raising my
voice or using critical terms of like
that's a dumb idea. There are better
ways to argue or to debate and I was
doing it the bad way. I think I got away
with that for a long time because I was
right many times uh or driven. But
ultimately the best way is to have the
skills to do that. Well, you mentioned
in some of your writing that when you
lost your job as a VP at the startup
that one of the big sources was sneaky
corporate politics and let's say you
someone was in a leadership role and
they want to kind of get ahead of that.
What's the story behind the politics
there and how do you do it right or how
do you do it well to prevent that kind
of situation?
>> Well, there's two things going on.
First, when you're loud and abrasive and
confrontational, if you are, if you push
too hard, people who disagree with you
will stop telling you. They'll just stop
talking to you and start talking to
others about you instead. So, you want
to be careful when you are strategically
annoying that you aren't so much in
people's faces that you shut them down
and they go behind your back instead.
So, I kind of cause those situations by
causing people to say, "This guy's
crazy. we'll just go see if we can get
him removed. The second thing is I
didn't build enough alliances with
others. So let's say I disagreed with
person A very strongly. I didn't have
enough alliances or close enough
relationships with B, C, and D so that
when A would go to them, they would tell
me. Instead, when A went to them,
they're like, "Yeah, we see he's a
problem." And you know, it became,
again, I literally dug my own grave in
hindsight. And what I would say you need
to do is yes how you interact with
person A matters having the social
skills there but the other part is
building your set of allies or at least
people who respect you enough to include
you in the conversation and I failed to
do that. I didn't realize as an engineer
and I think many engineers fall into
this. We think that being right is what
matters and we don't realize that
relationships and how other people feel
about it matters just as much. Even to
the point where people will pick a worse
solution that feels more comfortable.
That happens all the time.
>> It sounds like you got repeated feedback
through situations that happened in your
career early where soft skills might
have been something that could have been
better and later in your career it
sounded like it was one of your
strengths. So I'm curious what made you
flip the switch?
>> Yeah, it is this incident of being let
go the second time where I was a layoff
of one. It was more direct than the
first time I left a company. It was very
pointed and I also had trouble because
it was right after 911 and and sort of
the first dot bubble. I had trouble
finding another job. And so that really
there was an interviewer. I was at an
interview and I was telling the story of
all my accomplishments and trying to get
the job. And he said, "Everything you
say sounds fine, but I just really
struggle to believe that if you were
that valuable, these companies, even
though they were struggling, wouldn't
have found a way to keep you around."
And I actually realized he was kind of
right. Like if I were that valuable,
they'd have kept me around. And so I
asked that caused me to think, okay,
what's the gap? The gap isn't my
technical skills. It isn't my ability to
drive and get projects done. It's my
ability to work well, play well with
others. And so then I got deeply into
and I recommend this to people, the
psychology of work and what motivates
people. Of course, how to interact, how
to ask questions, how to draw people in.
Um, as an engineer, we love, we're
taught in school to make statements. The
statement is the answer is this, the
method is that, the code should be this,
as opposed to ask questions. Once I sort
of realize, oh, look, this works. I can
lead and motivate people and inspire
them and and this is a fun puzzle. Then
I was hooked. And so now I study it kind
of full-time in a way. I saw, you know,
after you kind of worked at some
startups, you decided to move across the
country and take the job at Amazon,
which is pretty big move. I'm kind of
curious what the story is behind that
move and how did you know it was worth
joining Amazon?
>> This is a fun story I don't know if I've
ever told. I was working at that search
engine, LOS, and Los had a partnership
with Barnes & Noble. Barnes & Noble knew
nothing about being online at that
point, but they wanted to be. And so
they partnered with this online company
and part of my job was to figure out why
they were losing to Amazon. So I had
some calls with some people at Barnes &
Noble. I talked to them and what they
were doing and what they could do and
what they couldn't do. And so I learned
about Amazon by viewing them as a
competitor to our partner. And that's
what taught me like, oh, this Amazon
company is completely different, way
ahead of what was called bricks and
mortar, right? Like the physical world.
Then when Amazon called me, because they
actually reached out, a recruiter
reached out, I was able to talk about
how I knew Amazon as this competitor to
Barnes & Noble and how I had been
impressed and what I had done with
Barnes & Noble to try and help them
compete and how hopeless that looked.
And I think that probably appealed to
Amazon of like, okay, this guy is seeing
where we're going. As for taking a risk,
you know, I was at yet another startup
that was struggling with product market
fit and funding, and Amazon wasn't. So,
there was both the the being impressed
with them, but also being sick. You
know, Amazon was had IPOed at that
point, was a public company. They were
not profitable, but they still looked
they were 10,000 people, which now
they're way over a million, right? So
10,000 seems quite small. But to me,
working in firms of dozens or hundreds,
it was like, oh my god, this has got to
be stable. Look how big it is.
>> You know, when you when you got to
Amazon, I saw you were hired in as a,
you know, senior manager and eventually
you got promoted to um, you know,
director first and then later to a VP. I
think like there's not a lot of
information on what those jumps even
look like. So, I'm curious, you know,
for instance, the promotion to director.
What What is even the the expectations
like what does a promo like that even
look like?
>> It's interesting. Times have changed.
Amazon was smaller. I remember seeing
the paperwork to become a director and
the paperwork said to be a director in
Amazon, this person should be one of the
100 most important leaders in Amazon.
But of course it was already outdated
and there were well over a hundred
directors uh when I when you know when I
saw this. So things were moving fast
because it was a hyperrowth company.
What they were looking for specifically
was someone who could lead a business or
an effort on their own that only needed
highlevel goals. And in my case my
promotion specifically came from some
good luck and a good decision. So I
could then I think this is common
promotions either happen as what I call
lifetime achievement awards. Someone's
there and they do good work and they do
good work and eventually the process
grinds away or they have an outsiz
event. In my case, two things worked in
my favor. The first is there was a
project that came up. I made a very
high-risk call. My management disagreed
with doing the project, but they had
told me show that you can be the leader.
So, I specifically said to my SVP, I
said, "Unless you order me not to do
this, double negative. Unless you order
me not to do this, I'm going to do it."
And he's like, "Great. Hang yourself."
Well, I built the project and it worked.
And it turned out to be a big success.
So, in my eventual promotion, the key
line was it was a partnership with Teo,
the DVR company. The key line was
without Ethan, we wouldn't have had Teo.
So I kind of made my chops on being a
high judgment decision maker who could
make things happen. The second thing is
my VP in between level uh was leaving. I
had gone to him and said look I want to
be promoted to director and I had
threatened to leave very politely if I
wasn't promoted. Well, it was going to
make him look really bad if he left and
I left cuz the project would fall apart
as opposed to being threatened by my
threat in a way. He had pressure to like
make sure he secured me. And the
specific words I use are interesting.
When I threatened, the learn soft
skills. I was very careful. And the
words I use, I said, well, my career is
very important to me, which no one can
argue with that. my career is very
important to me and I need to know if
it's as important to Amazon because if
it's not as important to Amazon as it is
to me I have to think about that and of
course you can hear the like hey take
care of me or I'm out but I never said
anything that someone could be like
screw you you can't threaten us I just
said my career is really important to me
and if it's not as important to you you
know as the representative of Amazon
then I need to think about that it's led
me to the philos philosophy that you can
find polite and civil ways to raise any
topic. And so my promotion came because
I proved I could lead a business and
move Amazon video forward and because I
again strategically annoying. I was
willing to put pressure on it. That boss
wouldn't have done anything if I hadn't
been pushing. He wasn't the sort of guy
who was just like, "Oh, I should
probably promote Ethan." It was 100%
because I put the squeeze on. I was
like, "Well, up or out." That wording is
is so it's it's subtle, but it's so
good. You know, I could imagine that
have gone way worse if you had said, "I
need this promotion. You need to help
me." Rather than kind of implying it and
being polite with the wording. And I
think I've seen in many people's uh
careers as well that sometimes their
growth comes from being politely pushy.
You know, maybe they not exactly
threatened to leave, but it's it's clear
that they're asking for something and
the manager feels the demand of that.
Not in a stressful way, but just in a
when they're thinking of who to promote,
they kind of that's the first person on
their short list because they're asking.
As a leader, you know, people won't like
to hear this. It's I I believe in
telling the straight truth. It's one of
my tagline. As a leader, there have been
times where I have had two equally
qualified people on my team uh or you
know approximately equal and one of them
is agitating for the promotion and
threatening to leave and the other is a
nice person who's willing to wait and so
they wait. And a lot of people say,
"Well, you just rewarded the jerk."
Maybe, but I had a triage. I'm going to
get one promotion done this quarter or
this year because it takes work and you
only need so many leaders at the next
level. and I have a very realistic
choice of move up this person and keep
them even though I'm a little bit being
held hostage or move up this person and
lose the other one. I'd like to tell you
I always did the right thing and you
know help the team player, but I I can't
actually tell you that's true and I
certainly wouldn't tell you other
leaders do that because we have to think
about our short-term problems to some
degree and it's not a perfect world. And
so, yeah, if you're that person who's
expecting to be rewarded because you're
the silent hard worker who's always
collaborative, you know, maybe you
dislike me for it and you're like, well,
you sound like a bad boss. I'm actually
willing to tell you the truth and tell
you that almost everyone's doing what
I'm doing. They're just not telling you.
So, I don't know, bad, good, it's the
reality. you mentioned in your promotion
story, you said explicitly there's a
wording in your promo packet or
somewhere that said, you know, X would
not have happened unless Ethan was
there. And I think that's a really
important distinction when it comes to,
you know, crediting and and stuff like
that and promos. There's a lot of people
in big companies, there's multiple
people involved and, you know, people
ask, should I hoard it so that I get
credit or what? But really all that you
need is that that narrative is obvious.
If we pull Ethan out of this, that
wouldn't have happened. And if that
narrative is true, you get credit. And
that's often what drives these these
promos.
>> You know, if that project would have
just been fine, it wouldn't have hurt
me. I might not have gotten promoted,
but it wouldn't have hurt me. But if it
had blown up, I was the one who pushed
for it over the leadership's not
disagreement but advice not to do it.
And so had had I gone against that
advice and then it been a big disaster,
you know, that that could have very
easily cut the other way, which I think
gets the part of the point. If you want
to grow rapidly, you're going to have to
take some risks. But the risks are
recoverable. Remember, I was also a jerk
earlier in my career and lost some roles
and I still became an Amazon VP. Like
venture capital, taking some risks and
having some of them work out and some of
them fail still moves you forward faster
than always playing it safe. And if I
have any one regret, it's actually that
I didn't take more risk. I could have
gone further. I think like if I had my
career to do over again, I'd probably
take a lot more risk. By the time I was
trying to become a vice president, I had
been at Amazon a long time, I finally
truly understood how everything worked.
And that was a longded process where I
lined up stakeholders. I got my manager
on board to support me. You know, I had
a good relationship with my manager,
something a lot of people struggle with.
I was lucky enough that my vice
president was stable in his role for
about 2 and 1/2 to 3 years while we
worked the process. My timing was good
because he was reorged within 6 months
and after that. So had I been just 6
months later, I'd have had a new boss
and it would have, you know, been a
setback for sure, you know, rebuilding
trust and all that. So I can go more
deeply into it. The big thing I did
there is I've developed this idea I call
the magic loop which is working with
your leader, your manager to figure out
what they need you to do and then form a
partnership with them that amounts to
I'll do everything you need done. You do
you do one critical thing which is make
sure I'm rewarded for it. And that's our
deal is I can either work for you as a
standard cog in a box or I can really
push and go above and beyond, but
there's got to be a payoff and and can
we line up and agree to that? And my
manager, I remember he came to me one
day, my vice president said, "Okay, I'm
going to try and get your VP promotion
through this cycle. I'm going to do
everything I can. I can't promise you
anything." But he was at a place where
he's like, "Okay, we're gonna take the
shot. I'm gonna lay my reputation on
it." And I had, it took two and a half
years to get him to where he was ready
to put his credibility down. Uh, luckily
that paid off, right? We both got it
done. He was happy, I was happy.
>> That partnership makes a lot of natural
sense. I mean, you help your manager,
your manager helps you, and they want
you to grow. People think managers are
withholding promotions at any level.
That's not true. Speaking as a vice
president, I want all the directors I
can have because the better my team is,
the easier my job is. So, I want high
performers. I want you to be good
enough. I want you to have the skills,
but I can't do that for you. So, people
say, "Why didn't you promote me?" And
I'm like, "You did not promote yourself.
You did not get there." If you can get
there, I want that. It's good for me. I
know you have a story from, you know,
right when you started at Amazon where
there was a high performer on your team
and you established that partnership
with them, but you weren't able to get
their promotion and they ended up
leaving. Yeah. So, I had a star young
engineer who uh made this deal with me
and I made the deal in good faith. He
said, "Oh, I will help ship our very
first version of our product. I'll do
whatever it takes. You get me from what
we called SDE1, which was the new
college higher level to SD2." And I'm
like, great, got it. I'll do that. I had
always worked at startups where when you
wanted to promote someone, you just kind
of went to your boss and maybe HR and
said, "We should promote this guy." And
you did it. Amazon had a process and
they only did promotions twice a year
and they had a cycle. Our project launch
was a mess. Not his fault, but we had
problems. I was busy looking at the
problems and trying to, you know, fix
the product. The cycle came and went.
He's like, "Hey, where's my promotion?"
I went and asked like, "Oh, how do we do
this?" and they're like, "Yeah, you can
do that in the spring, maybe." The the
factor was my and I've written about
this very publicly. I own it. It was my
ignorance. And so, the problem is we
made a deal in good faith that I didn't
know how to keep. So, that's my error.
The advice for someone making the deal
is figure out is your manager a veteran?
Do they know what they're doing? You
know, do they understand the process or
do you? And this is a common problem
because people get new managers very
often. So even if I hadn't been the
idiot in this situation, uh it could
have been somebody else who was hired
in. Can do you understand the process? I
think part of the issue is that
engineer, which is not his fault, but he
also didn't know. And so it was an ugly
discovery for him like, oh, we missed
the date and sorry. He didn't know to
tell me like, hey, Ethan, you got to be
doing this. you know, there's a date and
you got now is that his responsibility?
It's not. It was mine. But the tricky
part is it's your life. And so if you're
the engineer in that situation, probably
people all know the story from scrum and
chickens and pigs, right? The pig is
committed. The chicken's only involved
in the ham and eggs restaurant. The
manager is the chicken in this. Their
life isn't on the line. It's you. You're
the one who's going to get hurt. So know
the process and make sure the manager is
like, "Okay, I'm going to do this." this
and you're like, "Okay, well, by
September 15th, are you going to have a
document done?" And if they say, "Why
does September 15th matter?" That's like
a warning sign, right? Why does that
matter? Oh, that's the deadline. Oh,
there's a deadline. Like that, you know,
that conversation would have been very
revealing if he'd have known to have it.
And I feel terrible about it. It's why
I've written about it publicly is I
don't want it to happen to anybody else.
So, this guy left. He joined another big
tech company. He's had an amazing career
there. It cost him a year. And I I feel
bad about that. But the truth is careers
are 20, 30 years long or more. Things in
life are going to cost you a year
sometimes. That's not fatal. So when you
hit that, I just wasted a year. You can
either mope it and be depressed or you
can move on. He moved on and was
successful. I've moved on and been
successful. You can you can make that
change.
>> So after you got promoted to VP, I saw
that you switched business verticals. or
you went to the Twitch partnerships or
managing the Twitch partnership and then
later into gaming. I'm curious, it
sounds like the Twitch acquisition was
right before you became kind of in that
role. Were you the VP in charge of
plugging them in or what's the story
behind that role?
>> Amazon's a big company. So, it had a
process that every time it bought a
company and we spent 970 million on
Twitch, so a billion dollars. They take
a VP and they make them kind of what
you'd call the integration liaison, the
the person who's going to facilitate
making sure you get your billion dollars
worth. The trick is they leave the CEO
in charge. So IT Shear, we talked about,
you know, you're aware of Imit. Imit was
still in charge of Twitch. I was not his
boss. Instead, I purposefully sought out
that role. We talked about working on
soft skills. I had become vice president
running Amazon's app store and I had a
team of 800. And so I was now very good
at running a global team of hundreds of
people. But that's where I had
authority. I decided to challenge myself
and go take a role where I had a goal,
help Twitch integrate, but I had no
authority. I was simply an advisor to
the CEO. I had no team. And I had to
achieve this goal without being able to
give this guy any orders. And here's a
guy who's just been made wealthy for
life. He's 15 or 16 years younger than
me. He's in a business that served
mostly teenagers and people in their
20s. You know, he's 33 or so. I'm late
40s at that point. How am I going to
influence him in how to run his sort of
millennial Gen Z business when I'm
neither? And I I I wanted that challenge
to work on my soft skills. So I gave up
the team of 800 to go figure out how to
do this. It's a fascinating story that
worked out really well and I really
enjoyed working with EMTT as well as of
course learning to live stream on Twitch
and all kinds of stuff.
>> When I see these founders with, you
know, rocket ship trajectories, I don't
know the exact size of Twitch at the
time, but maybe hundreds maybe low
thousands of employees at such a young
age. I'm curious when you work with a a
young founder like that as a seasoned
manager with tons of experience. What
are the gaps that you notice in someone
that has such a unique management
trajectory or are there none?
>> Oh no, there were plenty of gaps. I
think EMTT would agree with that if he
were with here with us. We might not
agree on what the gaps were. So first to
give you scope, Twitch was several
hundred employees at that point and grew
within the next couple years to be a
thousand. So he was on a very rocket
trajectory. The biggest problem was
Twitch was a classic venture funded
company. It was bleeding cash, you know,
at a huge rate. And in fact, one of the
gaps was in the beginning, Emit and
certainly members of his team didn't
even think this was a problem. Well,
they had always been able to get venture
money. And now the way they originally
looked at it, I remember people in
Twitch on the management team looking at
me and saying, "Well, now that Amazon's
bought us, you guys have lots of money.
Why do we need to worry about
profitability or advertising? Like, why
can't we just focus on the gaming?" And
my job was to help move them to
profitability. So, I'm like, "Whoa,
Houston, we have a problem. They don't
even see it as a worthy goal."
Meanwhile, you know, the management
chain above me, because I ultimately
reported into Andy Jasse, who's now CEO
of Amazon, he wanted profitability quite
soon. So, you're trapped between a a
group of people who are like, "Ah, why
does this even matter anymore? You guys
have all the money in the world." So,
that was one gap. Another gap that I
would say Emit learned the hard way over
time, it's very easy to be loyal to your
early employees, but not all of them can
scale. And so Emit went through a big
learning cycle of I'm gonna have to hire
in somebody over this person who was
with me from the beginning and I'm gonna
have to explain to this person who's a
friend of mine, love you. You're going
to make a lot of money because your
stock options are now Amazon shares, but
you're not going to remain whatever
chief product officer or fill in the
blank. And uh that was a that was a big
discovery I think for Emit that he had
to replace some friends or level them
and a few of them quit and were angry.
>> You you mentioned that you reported to
Andy Jasse the now CEO of Amazon and I
imagine you had some proximity to Jeff
Bezos or had been in meetings with them
comparing and contrasting the leadership
styles between the two. Is there
something that stands out from each or
maybe a story that you think illustrates
those things?
>> Yeah, so I knew Jeff pretty well. Yeah,
I'm not going to claim he's like a best
buddy of mine, but I've probably had
about 50 meetings with him and about 50
with Andy in different contexts. So, I
know them both, you know, spending
dozens of hours with them and working
for them. The biggest difference is
Jeff's the founder. And what that means
is he can take gamles with the company
that others won't. So, a story I
remember is in a budget discussion, our
chief financial officer was trying to
slow down Jeff's spending on something
and he said to Jeff, "Well, you know,
Jeff, we only have so much money in the
bank, trying to like just pump the
brakes a little because Jeff was let's
do this and let's do this and the price
tag's going up." And the CFO said, "You
know, Jeff, we only have so much money
in the bank." And Jeff looked at him and
this was the previous CFO to the current
one. And he said, "Well, Tom, how much
is that? Because I might want to spend
it." And he was just telling his CFO
like, "Thank you. Your job is to count
the pennies and my job is to allocate
them and don't don't confuse your role
and my role." And Andy is a more classic
I don't recall if he has an NBA. I think
he does, but he's a more classic
business leader. He's not going to tell
his CFO, you know, stick a sock in it.
That he's going to see that he has to
partner. And that's because it's not his
toy, right? He is the paid leader, but
it's not his company. And that no matter
how much I respect Andy, that's just
very hard to get over because when it's
your toy, Jeff definitely felt that he
could, you know, sort of take
metaphorically take the whole company to
Vegas and bet it on black, right? That
that like he had that right. I built it.
I can do what I want with it. Whereas
for Andy, he helped build it, but he has
to actually do what the board wants with
it and what Jeff wants with it. And
that's just different. Both Jeff and
Andy put great demands on me and other
leaders. For me personally, for my
style, I felt Jeff was emotionally
behind me and supportive. And I felt
Andy was kind of always waiting to see
if I'd screw up. And so if we brought in
10 executives who work for both of them,
not all of them have had that
experience. I found working for Jeff
much more inspiring and not just because
he was the founder, but because he
seemed enthusiastic. Andy seemed more
ready to ask more probing questions. And
I at least as a personality need that
leader who yes, they ask all the
questions, but then they're like, "Okay,
I'm on board. Let's do it. We'll do it
together." And I never got a like we'll
do it together from Andy. I always feel
like I got okay, it's your plan. You're
on the hook now. Let me know when it's
done. It didn't inspire me the same way.
>> You mentioned being scrutinized and I
saw that you had written about how you
started the prime gaming vertical with
some some peers and you mentioned that
it had failed multiple times. I'm kind
of curious, you know, what does a VP's
performance review look like if the
business vertical they started is
failing? So this is a flaw of big
companies because often when I say
something was failing, we would hit most
of our goals, ship this, build that, add
this feature. We might even hit some
financial goals, but we weren't
achieving the vision. The vision of
Prime Gaming, the original vision Jeff
wanted was to make Amazon a real player
in the video game business. At one point
his vision was how can we be as big as
10 cent which is the largest gaming
company in the world out of China. So we
met a bunch of goals but we were never
on track to become like that. And
certainly Prime Gaming has never done
anything like that. Amazon Game Studios
all the gaming pieces they're very
niche. So when I say it failed multiple
times I think it failed against the
vision. you can get a good review for
ticking all the boxes and hitting like
all these interim goals and not really
be on track for doing anything
significant. Right before I left the
Amazon App Store to join Twitch, I told
a peer I said, you know, this year I'm
going to hit every goal and it's going
to be meaningless. And the proof of that
in some ways is now 10 years later,
Amazon has shut down its app store. They
use it internally, I think, but all
external use has been, you know, for
phones and whatever. They they've given
up after 10 more years. Well, I saw that
coming 10 years ago. But big companies
can get lost in, well, we're hitting the
goals and they confuse hitting the goals
for doing something actually valuable.
The bottom line is I was rated well as a
VP every year of my career. And yet,
when I look at did some of the things I
do really succeed, I'm very proud that
we launched Prime Gaming and we put
Amazon in the game business, but it
hasn't gone anywhere. And it won't
surprise me if in 2, three, or 5 years,
Amazon shutters that. Now, it also won't
surprise me if they get some leader who
figures out how to make it big. But
there's a lot of sort of zombie products
in a big company that no one quite wants
to pull the trigger on shutting down
because that's a big decision and an
admission of failure, but no one really
knows how to make big either. So they
just kind of bump along.
>> It sounds like even forward-looking,
like being in it, you you hadn't
achieved the goals yet and you looked at
the goals and you said these are not
impactful. Did you ever have a thought
of let's make the goals more ambitious
or let's change the goals so that
they're the ones that align with the
vision?
>> Sure. The problem is you know you're
going to be judged on them. So there's a
tension between the goals you think
matter and the goals you have any idea
how to hit. So, I'll I'll I'll tell you
for the Amazon App Store, the goal was
somehow compete with Google on on
Android phones when Google comes
pre-installed and Amazon is a sideload
like that people have to decide they
want and then opt into. I had no idea
how to compete basically with an endemic
store, a pre-installed store on its own
phone. That was the goal. Of course, I
argued strongly against being judged
against that because I didn't know how
to do it. I would say other leaders who
came after me who were quite hardworking
didn't obviously didn't know how either.
For my review and my pay, I want goals I
know I can nail. And for the good of the
company, I actually want goals that I
have no idea how to do. And so, when I
said this, I was like, "Yeah, I'm going
to nail all these goals that I fought to
be measured on, and I'm going to miss
all these goals that actually matter
because I don't know how to do them."
And it turns out maybe they were
impossible. The the you know again if
you think about this aspiration oh
Amazon wants to be 10 cent in games.
Well this is like if you work at some
e-commerce startup saying well you know
Ryan we want you to take a goal to be a
second Amazon. How are you know you
might be like well I get why that would
be valuable. I do understand that's a
great vision but I'll pass. with your
tenure as a manager at Amazon, I kind of
want to talk about, you know, management
practices like, you know, stack ranking,
performance-based layoffs, pips, those
types of things. So, I'm curious, you
know, Amazon's pretty famous for stack
ranking and, you know, really
aggressively managing people out. Yeah.
Um, what are your thoughts on on these
types of systems? About 10 years ago,
Amazon ran an experiment where after
getting years of bad press for stack
ranking, they removed what was called
the unregretted attrition goal. So,
Amazon has a goal every year for what
they call unreged attrition, which means
people, it's a nice way of saying people
we want to leave. Um, and we don't care
if you pressure them into quitting or
they get fired. It's just there's a
number and you put people on a list of
folks you want out and you can either
improve their performance to where you
take them off the list, they can quit or
you can fire them. But you have to hit a
goal and it's usually like 7% a year.
Sometimes it's as low as four, sometimes
it's as much as seven. So Amazon uses
lots of words to kind of cloak this
process, but the bottom line is it's
fire the bottom 5% or so. Here's the
thing. When we remove the goal, managers
immediately stop having hard
conversation and talking to their
struggling performers because without
the pressure of having to do it, it was
just easier to focus on your good people
and let that problem person hang around
because it's not in a big company. It's
not costing your burn rate that you know
about or care about and you don't have
to have that unpleasant conversation and
you also don't have to be the bad guy.
One of the worst things about being a
manager is you may have someone who
isn't very good but is wellliked.
They're friendly. They are outgoing.
They bring donuts. They organize the
parties. Everybody likes them. And so
now you have to not only have a hard
conversation with them, but if you do
move them out or if they talk to other
people like, "Ethan's trying to fire
me." Then everybody's like, "Why are you
trying to fire Ryan? He's awesome. We
love him." Well, it may be that you know
you have lots of performance problems,
but other people aren't feing those. So
when we remove the goal, people stopped
having the hard conversation. So the
next year, Amazon put it back and it's
kept it every year since. So on the one
hand, many managers avoid actually
performance managing if they're not
forced at gunpoint. An unfortunate
truth. On the other hand, because
there's a list and because there's a
goal, you would be then be in a
situation where someone who had a chance
to succeed, maybe you had to put on the
list to make your quota. And you ask how
how how well the pips work. I think most
pips are a combination of dishonest and
or psychologically
unrealistic because once I've decided
that I'm going to put you on this list
or once I've decided you're enough of a
problem that I need to write up this
plan and have this ugly conversation
with you mentally I've already moved to
we have to get rid of Ethan, right? We
have to get rid of Ryan. They're not
good. recovering. It sort of doesn't
matter what you do unless it's amazing.
I've already decided and so my cognitive
bias is going to be self-fulfilling. Um,
so what I recommend, you know, this has
happened. I coach people. I have had
half a dozen people reach out to me for
coaching and say, "I was just put on a
PIP at Amazon. I I really want to
succeed. Help me." And I've tried and
they've all gotten fired. And so now
when people call me, this is funny. They
call me and they say, "I'm on a PIP."
And I'm like, "So, what you need to do
is spend that time on the PIP looking
for your next job because you're going
to be fired." And they're like, "No, no,
I'm going to overcome it." And I'm like,
"Good luck with that. Tell me what
happens." And 3 months later, I get a
note that says, "You were right. I was
fired." And the reason I state both
people I coach and people I don't is, of
course, you could suspect, well, maybe
I'm a lousy coach and I didn't dig them
out of the hole. But the people I didn't
coach got fired, too. It's a self like
once you're at that stage, it's going to
happen. Very few people ever dig out of
them. Now, I believe some managers in
their minds start a PIP with honest good
intentions, but at least in Amazon, you
have your HR business partner and your
boss asking you all the time, "How's it
going? When are we going to exit that
person? I need them on my quota." You
know, if you actually want to take
someone off a PIP, more than likely,
your manager is going to be saying,
"Well, who else are you going to put
on?" Because we still have to meet the
number. So you're then you're looking
around and you're like, well, I put the
lowest performing person on my team on
and now I'm being told if I take them
off of PIP, I have to put somebody else
on. So of course you're like, well, so
the conclusion is companies stink at
performance management. They don't train
managers how to do it. They don't train
managers how to have the conversation
early. They don't create a system where
you can talk to people and say, you
know, this isn't working out. Maybe you
want to leave because that opens you up
to a lawsuit. We just have a
dysfunctional performance system.
>> In your writing, you you wrote something
that said a manager can fire anyone they
want and HR is not there to protect you.
I would have thought there's checks and
balances to this that that is not true
or I guess I would hope that it's not
true. What What is stopping a manager
from from painting their report in an
unfair light? Or is there nothing
stopping that?
>> I love that you called this out. I agree
with what I wrote. The nuance is as a
manager I could get rid of any one
employee I wanted but I can't get rid of
every employee. And so if I create a
pattern where I'm driving one employee
after another out I will eventually get
caught and burned for that because we do
look at what is a manager's turnover
rate. My point was for any single
employee, I can absolutely, if I choose
to end that person's career at my
company. And at Amazon, it's as simple
as put them on this list. It's partly
who strikes first. So, by the time you
go to HR, I've already put you on this
list and told my story of why I think
you're bad. And now you're going, "No,
no, it's unfair. He hates me." Well, the
problem is the people all the people
they've heard from who are legitimately
bad are saying the same thing, right?
They're they're saying, "No, I'm
actually good. It's my boss hates me and
doesn't understand me." So, they hear
that story every day. So, when you
legitimately tell it and it's actually
true and it's just I hate you, you just
you end up sounding like everyone else.
And so, that's why it's stacked in my
favor. Now, I I have never done this,
but I've looked at the system and just
seen I have people all the time who say,
"Well, my boss told a lie about me."
Well, again, it's your word versus mine,
and I'm the one who's got the higher
level, maybe the more tenure. If I
choose to say, "Well, you know, Ryan
looks really busy, but he's mostly just
doing pull requests on other people's
code." I can downplay what you're doing.
Because see, I can tell this story of
Ryan is an amazing engineer. He makes
everybody's code better because he does
all these insightful reviews and he's
upleveling the whole team. That's
narrative one. Same facts. He did 700
pull requests this quarter or whatever.
Narrative two is, you know, Ryan
actually doesn't contribute much. he
thinks he does and he spends all this
time doing code reviews, but look at how
little he's actually written himself and
really he's just busy nitpick nitpicking
people and churning away. And sure, his
numbers look good, but those numbers are
actually a sign of the problem. Now,
I've taken your same performance and
spun it two ways. My point that people
aren't going to like is a manager can do
that. And maybe they're doing that
because they're a jerk and they've
decided you threaten them and they want
to get rid of you. Maybe they just have
a different view. You think you're doing
really valuable stuff and they don't and
they're saying what they honestly
believe. But the point is performance
that you would think is really easy to
measure like look at these numbers. Look
how many valuable code reviews I did can
be used either way. Nothing about
software engineering performance is so
objective. And so bad managers, truly
bad or evil managers do get caught
eventually. But clever managers, you
just want to get rid of one person would
be able to do that because they're in
the driver's seat. And more importantly,
they get to make the preemptive strike.
They get to tell the story about why
that person's a problem before that
person ever knows it's happening. And so
it's kind of like, yes, you can slap the
mosquito after it bites you, but it
doesn't take away being bitten. I mean,
it's it's unfortunate that that's true,
but it also illustrates the power of
storytelling in a way. The exact same
facts can be spun as a bad thing or a
good thing. So, people are going to hear
this and believe like, oh, see, managers
are just like personally firing people
because they hate them. I am sure that
happens. It's not in a manager's best
interest. They they are judged on
accomplishing their goals. that, you
know, good managers are trying to find
partners they can work with that will
help everyone achieve. I just want to be
honest that if you do have a difficult
boss and you make them angry and they're
a vindictive sort of person, beware they
hold like you're bringing a knife to a
gunfight. They're the one with the gun
and you're probably going to lose. If
you have a boss like that, don't get in
the knife or gunfight. Either figure out
what you can allow you to make friends
with them or find a different manager.
That's the actual point. Don't think
that somehow HR is going to come
investigate and rescue you.
>> Definitely
>> that just isn't what they do.
>> Um I want to be mindful of your time and
so I have you know one last question for
you which is that if you could go back
to your career right at the beginning
when you had just graduated and entered
the industry and give yourself some
advice what would that advice be?
>> So I'll answer in two ways. One of them
I did and one of them I really didn't.
The thing I would do is always prefer
high growth. My whole career was in
companies that were growing very
rapidly. And I compare that, people talk
about a career ladder. Well, my ladder
was always an escalator. I could climb,
but it was also moving up for me. And
so, the reason I got where I went is
because Amazon grew 100fold while I was
there from 10,000 people to a million.
Revenue grew like 80 times. The
escalator went up and I rode it. I also
climbed. So, that part I would keep the
same. The thing I would change is
probably not surprising you. I would
wake up much sooner to jobs are still
with other humans. It's great to be an
expert. It's great to be right, but
build the skills to have the
relationships, make the friends, get to
know lots of people, and you don't have
to be an extrovert to do that. I was a
classic introvert. I've certainly
learned to be more extroverted, but with
online tools like LinkedIn or pick your
tool, you can make a reputation and
build connections from the safety of
your keyboard in your darkened room all
by yourself. And so do do whatever works
for you, but get known because it works
so much better. You know, Amazon called
me for the job, not the other way
around. And you want that happening, so
build that reputation.
>> Awesome. Well, thank you so much for
your time, Ethan. Um, you know, at the
end of the interview, like to give you
an opportunity. Where can people find
you or is there something you'd like
people to check out?
>> So, the easiest place to find me is
either Ethan EvansVP on LinkedIn or
Ethan Evans.com, my website. I'm well
known for teaching classes about how to
get past the promotion hurdle we've
talked a lot about. So, if my style of
straight talk in this interview works
for you, then that's what I do all the
time. And if that's your flavor of ice
cream, then I'm your vendor.
>> Thanks so much, Ethan. Really appreciate
your time.
>> Yeah, my pleasure, Ryan. Thank you for
having me.
>> Hey, thanks for watching the show. I
don't sell anything or do sponsorships,
but if you want to support, you can
subscribe on YouTube or you can leave a
review on Spotify. And I'm always
looking for new guests to interview. So,
if anyone comes up who you think you
really want to hear their career story,
uh, let me know and I'll try to reach
out to them and get them on the show.
Thanks for listening as always and I'll
see you next time.